[Music]
hey folks
welcome to the dark horse podcast live
stream
and pet extravaganza yep number 48
number 48 that's right yes and all of
them have been pet extravaganzas to this
point so it should surprise no one who
was a long-term viewer i don't think
that's true actually we were keeping the
door closed for a while
oh the door right the pets the pet
baffle that is the door
yes yes it has prevented them from
accessing certain live streams so anyway
if you only tuned into those live
streams now we have more pets yes
all right um there is as always a ton
going on because it remains
2020 and i will say
i was looking at the calendar today and
you know what i noticed
let me guess it's no longer august it's
no lie that's one of the that's what was
the first thing i noticed yeah the other
thing i noticed is that we are exactly
one month out from election day is that
right is it november third i believe it
is november third yeah
okay um so that's remarkable and of
course
remarkable things are afoot in the
landscape of the election we had the uh
presidential debate which was certainly
worthy of a certain amount of commentary
and that was different
it was different it was different um and
then
also we have the presidential diagnosis
of covid which we will get to
later we are going to talk about that um
but to start off with
uh we are headed somewhere else how
would you like to
enter that discussion yeah i think i
wanted to start with an extended reading
actually from
joseph heller's uh catch 22. but
in order to set that up i wanted to
start with a shorter reading
from an article that i wrote that just
came out
in the swiss magazine schweitzer monat
in both german and english so if you
don't read german as i don't you can you
can read it zac of you just show my
screen
here for a moment i'm going to simply
start by reading the first five
paragraphs of this
of this piece which sets up the reading
from heller that i want to go to next
george floyd died under the knee of a
police officer in minneapolis in the end
of may
and people spilled onto the streets of
american cities outraged at police
brutality and racial bias and exhausted
by covet 19 lockdowns
in portland oregon where i live those
protests turned into riots nearly every
single night last summer
the homicide rate climbed to the highest
it's been in 30 years
one late night in mid-august a man was
dragged from his car and beaten by a
small band of thugs
the next day on a blue bird sky morning
some of the few stores nearby that were
not boarded up had shop owners out on
the sidewalks
cleaning up from the mayhem of the
previous night in this once bustling
downtown normal human activity is almost
entirely absent while the sun shines
and at night the chaos resumes fires are
started
people are assaulted human feces is
literally thrown around
some would tell you that my mentioning
these facts is evidence that i am on the
political right
in fact i am and always have been on the
left liberalism had many big wins in the
20th century
securing rights for women people of
color and workers the advent of
disability law environmental protections
to name just a few
but there is much more to be done even
as wealth grows the middle class is
disappearing
healthcare and education costs climb
while quality plummets
and we are polluting our air water and
soil at unprecedented rates extinction
rates are rising and habitat is
disappearing under the call for more oil
lumber and spaces for people to live
the gains made by 20th century
liberalism and any chance of confronting
the big issues still before us
are being eroded by a new ideology this
ideology call it the woke left or the
authoritarian left
traffic some blatant falsehoods and
untestable claims it is focused on
markers of identity
sex race disability and effectively
carves out ways to divide us
rather than unite us in our common
humanity
we are being told for instance that men
and women are exactly the same
indeed that sex itself is a social
construct this is a fiction
and threatens to disappear many hard-won
protections for women
nature magazine one of the world's top
scientific journals now inserts into its
news stories the claim that sex is
neither binary nor fixed
they do this even in articles that are
literally about differential outcomes by
sex
from diseases including cystic fibrosis
and coven 19.
and central to a season of protests that
are nominally responding to society-wide
racism we are asked
to believe that all white people are
guilty of the original sin of racism for
which there is neither cure nor
forgiveness
loyalty oaths are demanded admit your
racism or be shamed or even fired
if you are not in fact a racist
defending yourself against false claims
is itself
evidence of your racism self-defense is
taken as proof of guilt
it's a perfect 21st century kafka trap
so that's the beginning of this essay
that was published
a couple days ago um in both the glossy
hard copy of the swiss magazine and um
online and i was reminded
of uh of that piece from it
when you mentioned i think on our last
live stream or maybe it was our private
q a that we did
on sunday last week that is available to
people
on my patreon of uh the
great it's actually not called the great
loyalty oath campaign as we had said
it's called the glorious
loyalty oath crusade from
from joseph heller and this i will say
this is one of
i hope it's okay that i say this this is
one of the few novels that you have read
cover to cover and um and i mean you've
you have actually read a lot but as as
someone with a diagnosis that we can
discuss separately whether or not
it should be a diagnosis at all but of
dyslexia um
you you read when you have to and
fiction doesn't necessarily always seem
like the thing that's necessary right
well i love
fiction but i tend to like plays and
series and and other things you like to
watch your fiction i like to watch
the fiction they'll send it in through
your you know your eyes and your
language
um i still use it but uh
yeah yes yes yes um
so uh this is a four-page
excerpt from uh from joseph heller's as
i said catch 22. i forgot to look at it
so if
i can just say yeah yeah this is a book
actually my mom pointed me to it in
high school originally published 1955
1955.
my mom i think recognizing that i was a
little
you know different or something
did not everyone in your life noticed
that i guess they did and that i had
uh something of a problem with authority
yeah a little bit of a problem with
authority thought this book might be
just the thing
and it happens that um you know a lot of
it
resonated with me quite strongly so one
of the frustrations that i have
is that the book is actually not all
that well known in the modern era people
know
catch 22 itself but they don't they know
the concept the central
they don't even necessarily know what
the catch is but i know that a catch-22
is you know it's like a kafka trap
basically and
um the throughout the evergreen episode
i kept wanting to raise
this uh reference because it
fit perfectly but i knew nobody was
going to get it wow
that's i mean that's that's fascinating
and then this is
this is the problem with the with the
loss of understanding of history right
and and of historical texts and this
yeah this is not that deep history this
is what 65 years ago that yeah
published first um and so the central
catch 22
is if memory serves um if you
are uh sane enough
to if you're crazy you don't have to fly
but if you don't want to fly that's
evidence that you're sane
yeah there it is you know and then
you're supposed to go
that's some catch yeah yeah it's the
best there is
yeah which you're sorry in in the book
is constantly
facing things which make him whistle in
in deep admiration
and uh and concern for his and his
fellow
fellows lives yeah okay so this is from
relatively early in the book
um and just without really any context
i'll just i'll just read it okay
um let's see i'm sorry kitty you're in
the way
uh i wanted to start with okay here
and when we remarked when someone
remarked that major major was somewhat
odd
captain black announced that he was a
communist they're taking over everything
he declared rebelliously well you
fellows can stand around and let them if
you want to but i'm not going to
i'm going to do something about it from
now on i'm going to make every son of a
[ __ ] who comes to my intelligence tent
sign a loyalty oath
and i'm not gonna let that bastard major
major sign one even if he wants to
almost overnight the glorious loyalty
oath crusade was in full flower and
captain black was enraptured to discover
himself spearheading it
he had really hit on something all the
enlisted men and officers on combat duty
had to sign a loyalty oath to get their
map cases from the intelligence test
tent a second loyalty oath to receive
their flag suits and parachutes from the
parachute tent
a third loyalty oath for lieutenant
balkington the motor vehicle officer to
be allowed to ride from the squadron to
the airfield in one of the trucks
every time they turned around there was
another loyalty oath to be signed
they signed a loyalty oath to get their
pay from the finance officer to obtain
their px supplies
to have their hair cut by the italian
barbers to captain black
every officer who sported his glorious
loyalty oath crusade was a competitor
and he planned and plotted 24 hours a
day to keep one step ahead
he would stand second to none in his
devotion to country when other officers
had followed his urge and introduced
loyaltyos of their own
he want them one better by making every
son of a [ __ ] who came to his
intelligence test signed two loyalty
oaths and three
then four then he introduced the pledge
of allegiance and after that the
star-spangled banner one chorus
two choruses three choruses four
choruses
each time captain black forged ahead of
his competitors he swung upon them
scornfully for their failure to follow
his example
each time they followed his example he
retreated with concern and wracked his
brain for some new stratagem that would
enable him to turn upon them scornfully
again
without realizing how it had come about
the combat men in the squadron
discovered themselves dominated by the
administrators appointed to serve them
they were bullied insulted harassed and
shoved about
all day long by one after the other when
they voiced objection captain black
replied that people who were loyal would
not mind signing all the loyaltyos they
had to
to anyone who questioned the
effectiveness of the loyalty oaths he
replied that people who really did owe
allegiance to their country would be
proud to pledge it as often as you
forced them to
and anyone who questioned the morality
he replied that the star-spangled banner
was the greatest piece of music ever
composed
the more loyalty oaths a person signed
the more loyal he was
to captain black it was as simple as
that and he had corporal kolodny signed
hundreds with his name each day so that
he could always prove he was more loyal
than anyone
else the important thing is to keep them
pledging he explained to his cohorts
it doesn't matter whether they mean it
or not that's why they make little kids
pledge allegiance even before they know
what pledge
and allegiance mean to captain plichard
and captain wren the glorious loyalty
oath crusade was a glorious pain in the
ass
since it complicated their task of
organizing the crews for each combat
mission
men were tied up all over the squadron
signing pledging and singing and the
missions took hours longer to get
underway
effective emergency action became
impossible but captain plichard and
captain ran were both too timid to raise
any outcry against captain black
who scrupulously enforced each day the
doctrine of continual reaffirmation that
he had originated
a doctrine designed to trap all those
men who had become disloyal since the
last time they had signed
a loyalty oath the day before it was
captain black who came with advice to
captain plichard and captain ren as they
pitched about in their bewildering
predicament
he came with a delegation and advised
them bluntly to make each man
sign a loyalty oath before allowing him
to fly on a combat mission
of course it's up to you captain black
pointed out nobody is trying to pressure
you
but everyone else is making them sign
loyalty oaths and it's going to look
mighty funny to the fbi if you two are
the only ones who don't care enough
about your country to make them sign
loyalty oaths
if you want to get a bad reputation that
is nobody's business but your own
all we're trying to do is help milo was
not convinced and absolutely refused to
deprive a major major of food even if
major major was a communist which milo
secretly doubted milo was by nature
opposed any innovation that threatened
to disrupt the normal course of affairs
milo took a firm moral stand and
absolutely refused to participate in the
glorious loyalty oath crusade
until captain black called upon him with
his delegation and requested him to
national defense is everybody's job
captain black replied to milo's
objection
and this whole program is voluntary milo
don't forget that the men don't have to
sign
pritchard and rens oil to youth if they
don't want to
but we need you to starve them to death
if they don't it's just like catch-22
don't you get it
you're not against catch-22 are you dr
nico was adamant
what makes you so sure major major is a
communist you never heard him denying it
until he began accusing him did you
and you don't see him signing any of our
loyalty oaths you weren't letting him
sign any
of course not captain black explained
that would defeat the whole purpose of
our crusade look
you don't have to play ball with us if
you don't want to but what's the point
of the rest of us working so hard if
you're going to give major major medical
attention the minute milo began starving
him to death
i just wonder what they're going to
think up at group about the man who's
undermining our whole security program
they'll probably transfer you to the
pacific dr nika surrendered swiftly
i'll go tell gus and watch to do
whatever you want them to do
uppit group colonel cathcart had already
begun wondering what was going on
it's that idiot black off on a
patriotism binge colonel korn reported
with a smile
i think you'd better play ball with him
for a while since you're the one who
promoted major major to squadron
commander
that was your idea colonel cathcart
accused him petulantly i never should
have let you talk me into it
and a very good idea it was too reported
coronal corn since it eliminated that
superfluous major that's been giving you
such an awful black eye as an
administrator
don't worry this will probably run its
course soon the best thing to do now is
send captain black a lawyer
a letter of total support and hope he
drops dead before he does too much
damage
colonel korn was struck with a whimsical
thought i wonder
you don't suppose that embassy will try
to turn major major out of his trailer
do you
the next thing we've got to do is turn
that bastard major major out of his
trailer captain black decided
i'd like to turn his wife and kids out
into the woods too but we can't he has
no wife and kids so we'll just have to
make do with what we have and turn him
out
who's in charge of the tents he is you
see
cried captain black they're taking over
everything well i'm not gonna stand for
it i'll take this matter right to major
to coverly himself if i have to
i'll have milo speak to him about the
minute he gets back from rome
captain black had boundless faith in the
wisdom power and justice of major
discovery even though he had never
spoken to him before and still found
himself without the courage to do so
he deputized milo to speak to major to
cover leave for him and stormed out
impatiently as he waited for the tall
executive officer to return
along with everyone else in the squadron
squadron he lived in profound on
reverence of the majestic white-haired
mage with the craggy face and jehovian
bearing
who came back from realm finally with an
injured eye inside a new sailored
eyepatch
and smashed his whole glorious crusade
to bits with a single stroke
milo carefully said nothing when major
to cover lee stepped into the mess hall
with his fierce and austere dignity the
day he returned and found his way
blocked by a wall of officers waiting in
line
to sign loyalty oaths at the far end of
the food counter a group of men who had
arrived earlier were pledging allegiance
to the flag
with trays of food balanced in one hand
in order to be allowed to take seats at
the table
already at the tables a group that
arrived earlier was singing the
star-spangled banner in order they might
use the salt and pepper and ketchup
there
the hubbub began to subside slowly
as major to coverly pause in the door
with a frown of puzzle disapproval
as though viewing something bizarre he
started forward in a straight line
and the wall of officers before him
parted like the red sea
glancing neither left nor right he
strode indomitably up to the steam
counter and in a clear
full-bodied voice that was gruff with
age and resonant with ancient eminence
and authority said
gimme eat instead of eat
corporal snark gave major to coverley a
loyalty oath to sign
major decovery swept it away with mighty
displeasure at the moment he recognized
what it was
his good eye flaring up blindingly with
fiery disdain and his enormous old
corrugated face darkening and
mountainous wrath
gimme eat i said he ordered loudly in
harsh tones that rumbled ominously
through the silent tent like claps of
distant thunder
corporal snark turned pale and began to
tremble he glanced toward milo
pleadingly for guidance
for several terrible seconds there was
not a sound then milo nodded
give him eat he said corporal snark
began giving major to coverly eat
major to cover lee turned from the
counter with his tray full and came to a
stop
his eyes fall on the groups of other
officers gazing at him in mute appeal
and with righteous belligerence he
roared
give everybody eat give everybody eat
milo echoed with joyful relief and the
glorious loyalty oath crusade
came to an end so yes for months i
harbored the desire to say
give everybody eat and have the madness
come to an end
but i knew it would have been lost on
everyone you didn't have the authority
to do so
no you didn't you you had not returned
from rome with one eye
bandaged and the eminence of a long
military
career behind you what we needed was an
adult
as we need now an adult with the
eminence and the authority unfortunately
to come in and say this will stop
well this will stop i wasn't imagining
in my wildest dreams that i had the
authority to do it but what i was
imagining was that the reference would
cause
people who were engaged in this loyalty
[ __ ] to recognize what they had
become
and suddenly become so embarrassed that
they would withdraw it but
and i think i can think of a few people
who were
privately supportive of us and who were
publicly on the fence who who for whom
that would have caused a pivot
right and i think probably in every
organization where this is happening
uh that is that is true but is it
widespread
is it widely known enough uh for it to
cause
uh a substantial fraction of people you
know a population large enough to
to cause a tipping point uh to to
recognize it and to reflect on
themselves what they're doing
probably not no there is
i think no chance that those circuits
are still
active somehow a huge fraction of the
population
becomes what they hate and never
realizes that that's what
what has happened and so it's easier to
do so when they're handed language
that makes it appear that they're
cloaking themselves and that makes it
appear that they are working on the
right side of history
and for truth and justice for all and
for black lives matter and all of these
all of this language you know they're
they're anti-fascists
um and you know they're anti-fill in the
blank phobe
whatever it is and and no they're not
they're they're
they're working on behalf of a kind of
great loyalty oath campaign
and what will they do with you if they
actually win which they might
right and you know the blind spot is
created by the fact that you know we can
all
sort of see the nationalists
the petty nationalists running away with
a loyalty oath campaign
to the flag or to the nation or
something like that and these people who
you know frankly don't like the nation
cannot
see that it is the same damn process
they are employing that it is
you know blind allegiance to some other
thing that
is driving them but the loyalty oath
part of it is completely generic
right well that i mean this this is
exactly it right that this
that these kinds of human responses to
situations in which
um someone wants to accomplish something
and others can be
caused to follow along um no no ideology
there there are no ideological or belief
bounds
on whether or not such a strategy or
such tactics will be effective
and so you know when we are told ah but
this isn't
you know this isn't that because those
people believed something else
doesn't matter tactic and belief are not
the same thing
and there's really i think no
relationship between them inherently
at least over in in this kind of space
that we're talking about
yeah the irony is that
i i must have had this thought a hundred
times in the last few years
is that what the folks who are deploying
one wrong idea after another really need
is a high quality college education
right and the fact is you know it is
normal it's childlike but it is normal
to have this sense that your cause is
different and therefore it's not
vulnerable to becoming
this you know caricature but
you know just the simple benefit that
would come from people
understanding the rawsian veil of
ignorance
you want to give a two-sentence
description of it yeah the idea is that
the only
legitimate policy is policy that is
indifferent to who is
deploying it if the value of the policy
you're advocating requires that you're
the one administering and
as soon as the enemy is administrating
it you're going to hate it um then you
shouldn't want it so the idea
so that is the that is the relative
unveil of ignorance that we should all
aspire to and that
we should seek in our in our laws and
our in our degrees right it's the only
stable thing because otherwise what you
get is everybody advocating policy that
puts them
ahead while they're you know nominally
in a position
to do it or in a power situation that
they can pull it off and then they
suffer from it on the other side
and so you know that one idea has just
tremendous
power for for one thing you see it in
places you don't even really expect it
like the the claim that we sometimes
make that people
end up scratching their heads about with
respect to
uh patriarchy right that there's
something hollow about this claim of a
patriarchy
what is it it's that the genes live
in a rosian veil of ignorance situation
which is if they make rules
that put males at advantage because
they're in male bodies in a position to
do so
then the half the time they end up in
female bodies they suffer the downside
of it
which doesn't mean that the rules are
fair but it does mean
it isn't that the genes have put men
ahead of women because the genes are
neither
the genes are both okay i don't think we
want to spend much time here but
my pushback to that would be the genes
uh so long as they are transmitted into
future generations don't actually give a
damn about what the individual's
lives are that they are contained in and
so the fact that there have been
clearly many societies through history
that have put women into a position of
being denigrated uh through any number
of mechanisms
uh would would seem to kind of put the
lie to
to what you just said partially
precisely because individual lives
still end up propagating the genes in
the bodies
and you can see how a proper college
education would emerge from exactly this
discussion because the point is as soon
as you see that the genes do live in the
situation and yet you have a situation
where things are unfair in a predictable
direction
why because the individuals don't matter
and then you start to see
they don't matter from the perspective
of the genes which is not interesting
but it is true
right yes then the question is uh
okay what are the genes up to and how
much do i like it
and the answer is they're up to a lot of
things and more than half of it you
probably wouldn't like
and what does that mean about our
ability to do something different which
gets you to
free well and all of the other things
well and there and this is this is
exactly and i feel like this is one of
the places that we started almost every
single
you know college program that we ever
taught which was
we want to provide you with the
evolutionary toolkit to understand as
much as possible about what it is that
you do and why you do it
so that you are most fully armed
to do that which is against the will of
your genes
when the genes have things in mind in
mind in quotes
um that are actually not honorable and
not good for society or yourself
or both right and um
to cap it off the
recognition of what the genes should
want if their purpose is to advance
themselves into the future
as far into the future as they can get
then it will
ultimately cause them to favor
patterns that result in people looking
at each other through a lens of how
related
are we and therefore how much do i view
you as a competitor
versus a collaborator which is of course
the basis of
racism of most warfare of genocide
tribalism of all sorts of well but
there's other kinds of tragedies
not of all sorts right tribalism of its
most basic sort
of it's certainly the earliest types
right and so
the because phenotypic markers of
identity
were a were a tool to be used to
identify whether or not it was friend or
foe you were looking at
and this is this is ancient and
it is that does not make it honorable
and indeed it is one of the things that
we should be
fighting against most strenuously but
pretending it doesn't exist
makes it more likely that it will
continue to exist and if you were gonna
fight it
the way to fight it would be to
understand what it was made of and
what the countervailing forces are
because the counterfailing failing force
exists also
and the united states is the prime
example of an experiment
with stabilizing that countervailing
force there are reasons for us to
collaborate irrespective of how related
we are
which is the thing that is most special
about this country so
the irony of a bunch of woke people
attacking uh the foundational principles
of the nation
and the epistemology on which it is
founded when the alternative is actually
let's calm down and have these
discussions with full nuance and you
will discover
that the enemy isn't what you thought it
was and the solution isn't what you
think it is
and there is a way to get there but
there's no shortcut
right right so actually um i know
we weren't going to go here just yet but
um this might be
the moment uh just to show one
one new thing that's happening with the
woke uh hold on just a second zach
um if i can pull this up here
okay here we go um so the
who are these people this is the
mathematical association of america has
tweeted it is time for all members of
our profession to acknowledge that
mathematics is created by humans
and therefore inherently carries human
biases until this occurs our community
and our students cannot reach full
potential
okay we're done zach we're done here
um so this this is a
classic conflation that is happening
over in wokespace
right the idea that the language that we
use to describe something
is the thing itself that has been
discovered
over in science and math land in general
we are doing is
discovering not creating so math is
discovered math is the underlying truth
of the universe
and the language that we use you know
the fact that we ended up with you know
newton's version of calculus and not
leibniz's
both of those are social constructs both
of those descriptions of calculus are
social constructs but the calculus
underlying
that was true between both of them is
true regardless of which human
language you use to describe it if the
mathematical association of america is
actually confused on this front they
need a complete reorganization
and really you just don't have any
business doing math if you think that's
true right
no we we need a new one if we knew what
if the organization that is the flag
bearer
for mathematical whatever it is
um association of america is confused on
this point then what we need
is a different mathematical association
of america that isn't confused on this
point because this point is
you know at the foundation yes right
yeah
exactly and so you know run this little
experiment it's not math but
actually you can do it in math space uh
the aliens step off the spaceship
they have had no contact with our
epistemology they just
see that something interesting is going
on in the earth they come to visit right
we put our scientists in touch with
their scientists
do they agree on the value of pi
my sense is they will agree exactly on
the value of pi which is not to say you
know obviously it isn't endlessly
repeating a non-repeating decimal so
it's not like it has
a precise value we can agree to but as
many decimal places as they will go
once we figure out the conversion factor
you know if they're 12
digited creatures and they use base 12
then oh you're talking about the actual
value of pi i thought you were talking
sort of like the the
the value of pi and having gotten to
where they are which is also true but
that's also true
they will 100 not only will they have
the same
value for pi that we have but they will
also be using it in the same ways that
we do because it is
necessary in order to do the kind of
work that you would need to do in order
to get a spaceship across a galaxy or
wherever these imagined aliens came from
so they will have gotten ever greater
precision
on pi we will agree on the value itself
there could if you want to steal man the
position of the mathematical association
here yeah
there are actually two ways that there
are probably more than two ways but
there are two major ways
that different cultures came up with
their approximations for pi
there's an inscribed polygon way which
is the greek way
yeah and there is an inscribed and is
outscribed the right
excrement excrimed i don't know way in
that the chinese
did it where they used two sets of
polygons
the language that's the description of
the underlying truth
well it's a process that undoubtedly
has a method so in this case it's a
method that results in a language
but the method is discovering the
underlying truth and the language
describes the method which describes the
underlying truth and we all it all
all roads keep on pointing back to the
underlying truth and if what if there
wasn't an underlying truth
then i don't know maybe we'd be doing
social modern sociology or something and
like
we actually know some good modern
sociologists but mostly
that field has been totally captured and
corrupted and it really is just a bunch
of
social uh constructions that are
meaningless but you can
do the experiment yourself you can
calculate pi
both ways the chinese way in the greek
way and you get the same value
and the aliens they may have a third way
or they may have settled on one of those
ways
and they will have the same value as
well and so the point is that
tells you that it isn't about who
described it
right and it also you know it say the
aliens
landed and uh
and they happen to use the chinese
method uh
that doesn't make the chinese method
better
it means that's what they discovered and
maybe it was better for their
environment
uh and you know whatever planet they
came from but
the fact that we have two different
discoveries on this planet and
i don't know you know did the maya
discover a third you know
the maya had astronomers the turks may
have had another
right so maybe there are yet more ways
to
to calculate pi and if the aliens
happened to use one of the ones that we
use that does not mean right away ah
well they got here therefore they're
better therefore it's best like no
as always it's context specific and when
it's math and you have multiple ways of
getting there
one of them may be better for some
circumstances and one of them may be
globally better
but you don't necessarily know that just
because someone
you know who arrived from a different
planet is using that for instance right
and you know the fact is the inferior
method still gets there it gets there
slower and i think in this case actually
it's the greek method
which gets there slower because it
starts you know if you inscribe a square
inside a circle you get a very rough
approximation
of pi so you keep adding sides to the
polygon in order to get a better and
better approximation
which is how you get further and further
into the decimal places
so one of these ways can be better but
it doesn't matter because it's like
discovering a mountain
right you know you may approach a
mountain from a really arduous path
where you may approach it straight away
same damn mountain
right that's good yeah and uh you know
and we could do this with chemistry too
right so the aliens step off the
spaceship what are the chances that we
will agree
you know on the fact of there being an
element iron right they will have a
different name for it but we will agree
on how many
uh you know uh nuclear particles it has
and how many electrons it's typically
orbited by
and we will agree on what the uh the i
the isotopes will be and how common they
are
yeah so anyway this thought experiment
just tells you
this kind of formulation is very
attractive right oh well if people
discovered it then their biases are in
it and it's like
the closer you get to the absolute
bedrock the less true that is
right right yeah and especially when
there are multiple roots in
and they've all arrived at the same
answer right exactly
okay so the question now is where do we
go from here
um we have several issues we want to
discuss
we want to talk about i'm a little
concerned about it but i think we have
to talk
about the um the events unfolding
in the presidential election space
okay with us exactly one month out
so we had that rather remarkable debate
um
seems to be almost universal agreement
about its nature
i do wonder how much of a thing like
that is the result of
people formulating their opinion
in concert with each other right because
people are paying attention to the
commentaries that's happening
yeah no this is i mean this is one of
the very many
problems with a social media era when
you have
very little time almost no one
you know if you're watching the debate
you have access to the constant
shattering and analysis
of lots of other people and you have to
actively decide i'm not going there
i'm not going to make i'm not going to
fill my head with what other people
think of this
until i have not only watched this but
sat on my
my sense of what it might mean for a
while preferably you know many
hours preferably sleep on it and see if
your position position has changed
before you start filling your head with
what other people
think about it and almost no one does
that now
on any number of topics and it really it
contributes
to a uh a less rigorous analytical
framework
uh absolutely and it's a it's a a
practiced art keeping your opinion
isolated long enough that you can
correct for
everybody else's opinion collapsing into
one because they formulated it with each
other in their ear
this is going to seem totally an aside
and it won't take more than
30 seconds but i'm reminded when i was
in
quito with my students from my first
study abroad in ecuador
and would have been 20 14 maybe
um very first day i was out with three
students and we were mugged
at knifepoint and i've written about it
um but
after it happened and before the police
showed up and before me
right in the middle of the thing but
after all the danger was over
uh i said to my three students
let's not talk about it just try to find
space in this crazy street scene right
now just even take two minutes to figure
out what you think you know
about what just happened and that
because we're going to be talk we're
going to be telling this story for weeks
now because we was just at the beginning
of this
this trip we had what 21 people that we
were going to go back to the host to be
like
this happened right let us let us first
figure out what we think we know without
any other input aside from our own
senses and our own experiences
and the fact that our stories converged
and then where they were different it
was because you know for me
i didn't have any color for the whole
thing like the entire scene was
remembered in black and white
and for someone else they didn't have
any you know any i don't remember what
like
any smells and um and so
we had this concerted understanding of
the event
which if we had just started talking
about it right away we would have had
very very much lower sense of whether or
not that is actually what had happened
or if one person's dominant sense of
what had happened had simply overridden
everyone else's sense
well and i think it actually hints at
this
tension between the two kinds of
history so yeah um
i will argue that history
is the fact that we use one term for two
different things
is very um
likely to cause conflict and it is
causing conflict so for example
you want to define the two types of
history you're talking about um
christopher columbus discovered america
okay
that's a kind of history what kind of
history it's
it's history like humans discovered math
yes it's eurocentric
and fictionalized right
um so we have the sense of christopher
columbus
you know arriving on the shores of north
america
the um you know and already that story
is just garbage
right right that didn't even happen
right right um first of all there was no
such person
cristobal colon was his name why we take
why we anglicize a name a historical
fact
right um makes no sense but the point is
what you're doing
in that case is you are creating a
narrative for a population
now that narrative is completely at odds
with
the um formation of nations
that are pluralistic right in other
words the idea that we send
that we americans celebrate columbus day
is preposterous even if you wanted to
celebrate something
about the historical fact of this person
arriving here because it
was meaningful arriving in this you know
hemisphere um you would celebrate the
historical aspect to it not the
fictionalized narrative because that
fictionalized narrative
is uh obviously in conflict with the
well-being of a large population of
americans
right the people who were here before
him right so
my point would be one thing history does
is it generates a story on which we
agree
it's a self-serving story on which we
agree and therefore the question of who
self is matters and then there's the
question of history which is
what actually happened and why right
what actually
so your first your first kind of history
which is actually happens
later it's sort of an um an overlay is
the narrative
which serves a purpose of basically
directing a population
and the friend and the second one that
you're about to talk about is at least
trying
um to describe factually what happened
with the understanding
that there is a kind of heisenbergian
truth about
like where you were standing and what it
is that you know the very act of
observation
can can change what you understand to be
true one thing i'll disagree with you on
is that i don't think the narrative
thing is an overlay on top of
what actually happened i think it's
actually a primary driver
and that the thing that you were as a
scientist protecting against
with you and your students formulating
your view of what took place separately
before you ever talked about it was the
fact that it is very normal
for human beings to settle on a story of
what happened and the important thing
about that story is not that it's
accurate
right now not not in my case but in the
case of people
coming together and agreeing on a shared
narrative and then
moving about in the world without
sharing right if you normally have
something happen to you with a group of
people
you deciding together what it was is
partially you
recovering some factual information and
partially you figuring out what's the
best story going forward
they're interleaved exactly and so the
actual study of history requires you not
to do that just as the actual study of
science requires you to ignore
what will advance your career in order
to see what's actually true
even if it embarrasses you right so that
suspension of the normal
instincts is necessary to the deeper
problem of sorting out how things
actually work so that you can
you know make a longer term kind of
progress it's an enlightened kind of
insight rather than a self-serving kind
of insight
so all right two kinds of history
in light of the um unprecedented
presidential debate this last week right
so in any case
the part of the problem is that our our
current environment now
allows arbitrarily large numbers of
people to compile their sense of what is
taking place
in real time you know people are on
twitter and elsewhere discussing what is
taking place as it happens as somebody
says something the interpretation of
what they meant unfolds
immediately and that that's very
corrosive
to the normal process of having a bunch
of different opinions about what was
said and what it meant
and what that implies going forward
which would then force a discussion that
would be at some level interesting we
skipped the discussion
and went straight to the knee-jerk
interpretation in this case maybe it's
two knee-jerk interpretations depending
upon
uh you know which twitter you're paying
attention to
right what do you mean which twitter
well presumably there are two
for americans there are two twitters
right there's
i mean and you actually stumbled across
this line earlier this week
where where somebody else stumbled
across it into you
right somebody who lives
over in democrat twitter right
posts at some point she's now deleted it
but she says
oh my god i stumbled into a large number
of people who think this woke stuff is
off the rails
who are they no no not just thatch what
she says so this is um
yeah this is interesting actually right
so she
hey she's got a vested interest in in
keeping
critical race theory alive because what
her business appears to be
is running dei diversity equity
inclusion trainings
and she tweets we just lost her well
there's a couple of them we just lost
our first client to trump's order to
to forbid uh critical race theory
training in
in federal organizations um you know i i
know i'm on the right side of the
history but i fear you know i fear this
being at the end something like this um
and then she says i'm running across
a cohort of people that seems to be
thousands strong and it's a lot stronger
than that but seems to be thousands
strong
who detest crt but also seem to be
anti-trump who are these people
right right and so many people myself
included
responded and said yes we're here and
we're reasonable
and we're all across the political
spectrum but yes some of us
are indeed democrats and always have
been and can't promise we always will be
but
um you know this this is true and
please you know please would you would
you listen would you be up for a
conversation i actually specifically
invited her to
to talk if she was willing and she
deleted the tweet
so and that i would point out is a
perfect analog for what happened
throughout the evergreen
riots where progress could be made with
an individual very briefly but it wasn't
durable
because they would get pulled back to
something yeah right so anyway
tragic that she sort of discovered
this land of people that didn't fit what
she'd been told the enemy looked like
and then basically burned the bridge i
mean
it's metaphorical but almost literally
yeah burned the bridge so she couldn't
get back there
her original the original missive on
twitter you know and it's a ridiculous
platform but
um seemed to suggest a curiosity
yeah a super an actual genuine surprise
and an openness because
she had presumably been in one of these
when one of these silos
and really truly believed the you know
the headlines from wapo and the guardian
and the new york times and everything
that if
you oppose critical race theory you are
a white supremacist
those are the same thing and no that's
not true
yeah it reminds me actually of the young
woman
i've described her situation before who
wanted to who sought me out as i left
the
the uh meeting the
nearly violent now quite famous meeting
at the top of the library building
at evergreen right 2017. sought me out
and basically her point when
when other protesters attempted to
shut down the conversation her point was
no i want to talk to him
and she actually says benjamin boyce
covers this very well on his channel she
actually says
he seems okay to me right i'm talking to
him and he doesn't sound like what
you're telling me he is and then
anyway they recaptured her the following
day well i'm sure she was made to sing
many choruses of star saying
spangled banner and sign many loyalty
oats she was in fact uh
forced to read a statement the following
day at
one of their rallies but anyway let's
not get uh lost here
so the debate happened and then two days
later maybe
we are now in the situation where i
believe it was
yesterday friday yeah so the debate was
wednesday night
or no the date was debate was tuesday
night and then friday morning very early
uh trump announced everyone on twitter
because that's how it happens
uh that he and melania had tested
positive for coping and tested positive
for cope
well it was well i've seen it was it was
friday morning his time it was friday
morning his time but before
bed i think um not that we know when he
sleeps but
um okay i mean we don't
instantly asterisk those aliens that
have landed and understand pi and the
value of pi
and the periodic table and it might look
different but it's got the same
underlying thing
just like to interest you guys
those aliens will also sleep they will
sleep
but i believe they will depart from our
perspective with respect to whether
there's always room for pie
ah yeah exactly having nothing to do
with sleep at all
right or pi in the sense that we will
agree on it but
right in any case we have
a remarkable situation surrounding the
president having contracted covet and i
want to talk a little bit about
what this actually implies but i also
feel an obligation to be extremely
careful in a way that i think is almost
not even possible okay
the problem is because
this issue was so thoroughly politicized
and frankly it was thoroughly
politicized on both sides but i think
trump was more political about kovid
it is very hard to avoid
the shakespearean
narrative that is unfolding or maybe
it's biblical but
the fact of um
trump having contracted kovid after
having
uh botched the initial
reaction to it downplayed its
seriousness all of this
it feels like karma it feels like come
up and it's
too many let's put it this way that
interpretation
it exists and it can't be avoided
the problem is there is and i want to
avoid it because at the moment you've
got the issue of a human being who has
contracted a disease
and gloating over that is unacceptable
but you also have the following thing
you've got this is the
commander-in-chief
this is now a fact of history and it
matters it matters to
all of our well-being what's more the
fact that the commander-in-chief
now has this disease which we are
learning a ton about but are still
new to um that it plays into this
election
in the final month in this way
sets us up for tremendous
vulnerabilities and uncertainty
and we have to talk about them so the
fact that those things
intersect with this you know natural
tendency that many are succumbing to
to schadenfreude is a problem because as
you talk about what happened
and why you will tread in the same
territory that people are experiencing
glee so i want to avoid the glee
but i want to traverse this territory
because frankly
our interests as a nation depend on us
doing it well
so i want to point out a couple things
one
the nature of this disease and trump's
parameters going into it
spell a very serious situation for us
there's
almost no way in which he
simply has a low symptom case emerges
from it
quickly and we go back to the election
as it was unfolding
by trump's parameters i imagine you mean
what comes to mind immediately are these
three things his age
his sex and his weight yep his his size
you know so
you know by some measures he's obese he
doesn't really look at but um you know
he's he's got he's got extra body weight
which we know
is uh is a risk factor he's in his 70s
definitely a risk factor and he's male
which um
it's you know it you have worse outcomes
in men than women
so all three of those are particular
risk factors all three of those are
particular risk factors and so
i think what we know is that just by age
and sex alone we are at double-digit
possibility
for death right that's not
a huge possibility but we're no i don't
think that's true you don't think that's
true
no i think the double digit if you're
just looking at age
um starts in in the 80s 80s
early 80s and it actually it's that's
like double or even more what it is in
the 70s
and the and the increased risk of bad
outcomes from covid for men versus women
is a couple of percentage points it's
not uh and i don't remember it it's
different across different studies but
you know it might even be as much as
like 55 45 but
i i don't think it's doubled at the very
least we are talking about
a non-negligible possibility much
more likely is a severe
case and a severe case could mean all
kinds of things that interface with the
national interest
quite badly like he has to go
on a respirator which i believe would
require him
to be sedated effectively it would put
us
in uh the territory where
pence would be acting commander-in-chief
right
and this i believe boris johnson was put
on a respirator when he contracted kovid
two three four months ago yeah and um
that was you know that
that was the biggest head of state that
had contracted it
yet and he's quite a bit younger yep um
so and uh i was speaking to a brit this
morning
and the fact is it was a month
before he was back to
uh anything like normalcy
so my point would be given trump's age
and uh other factors
we've got one month to the election
right that is effectively
very likely to be completely eaten up
by whatever this is so
i guess i would say unlikely that
presidential debates can happen which
changes the electoral picture
dramatically
we are already in the situation where we
are dealing
with transparently false medical
information or transparently misleading
medical information
and of course we are i mean we would be
no matter who he was
actually no matter what party and
how beloved or not the candidate was
uh the the advisors closest to him would
be putting
accurate and complete medical
information under
lockdown they just wouldn't be getting
out i don't think um
i agree and i also think there's
something so
many people have talked about the fact
that trump was
on stage with biden now they were quite
far apart
but this far apart business doesn't work
the way we initially thought it did
so if people have been tracking this
there was initial doubt
about aerosolized covid
so this this is a little bit technical
but initially it was thought
that the coveted particles were of the
nature
that they were heavy and therefore
breathed out they would tend to fall and
that's where the six
foot spacing idea came from what we now
understand is that this aerosolized
transmission happens where these
particles effectively hang in the air
indefinitely long they can see
it for hours it's possible you just
misspoke and i honestly haven't kept
track of the distinction between the
language
airborne versus aerosols so i thought
that you just said both of those were
aerosolized can we just
come back i believe that airborne is the
larger particles that are
affected severely by gravity and
therefore short distance
and so and aerosolize the smaller
particles which hang which hang for long
periods of time and can therefore go
great distances so and they are less
likely to hang
at least near the person who breathed
them out
in a place with excellent ventilation
hence the value of being outside because
no matter how good your ventilation is
inside
it's still an enclosed space and so
whatever was breathed out unless it's
already gone through you know the hvac
that has great scrubbers or something
it's still in the room somewhere yep um
so
there's a question i don't know that
anybody in the public knows the answer
to this
but there's a question i think so one of
the really important
stories buried somewhere in this is
the fact that the white house could not
effectively manage
trump's risk while he was playing games
about being brazen and wearing a mask
not as frequently as you should
and all these things you would still
think with all of the availability of
testing
and the availability and the ability to
modulate
exactly how people meet behind closed
doors and all of these things that the
white house would have been in a
position
to protect the president while playing
politics
with covet part of the problem is that
we just didn't know enough about how it
was transmitted
that's part of the problem i think the
other problem is they believed their own
press
and that there was a culture of bravado
that surrounded covid that began to feel
rewarding because they were more
liberated
to the extent that your enemies are
wearing masks and you have your full
facial expression
and so there was this culture of um
callousness and carelessness that
ultimately i think does play into
why the president and the first lady
have gotten sick and why so many people
in the white house seem to have gotten
sick um
and in any case what will have happened
during the debate right the debate they
were spaced far apart
that's good the president and his party
were not wearing masks that's bad
especially since multiple of them were
sick you've got multiple source points
yeah i i i need to fact check this but i
read
that um actually no one in the trump
family was
in direct contradiction to uh the rules
except for melania apparently melania
was for at least
some some of that no she wasn't when she
walked up on stage at the end yeah
obviously but um
that's you know good for her if true
yeah
um but here's the question
if they thought about covet as a serious
possibility in setting up that debate
then they could have managed air flow to
reduce the chances to near zero yes
i bet they didn't yeah right i bet they
didn't because i bet
other competing concerns like air noise
over microphones and things like that
would have dominated and they would have
thought
they're far apart good enough they don't
have covid we do a lot of testing
whatever they would have thought so
maybe we find out the answer maybe we
don't but the question has been raised
by many people
as to whether or not um biden might have
been exposed
right and you know yes they were far
apart
they were also uh vigorously
challenging each other vocally which is
sometimes looking at each other doing so
right and that you know that even if it
was
about uh airborne only and six that you
know that six foot
thing is is a poor approximation
under all circumstances really because
it doesn't account for um
for everything yeah um it's an average
and it only works if you're talking kind
of quietly
right right and it may even actually be
more stackier if you're just breathing
so as soon as you're talking loudly or
certainly if you're singing or shouting
um those droplets are going to be going
a lot farther right and they were
certainly in each other's
they weren't literally in each other's
faces but they were
as close as they could have gotten while
staying behind their lecterns
yeah and you know biden is notably
frail and so what what we have been
talking about on
yeah he's got two of the three risk
factors that trump does um he's just
he's not
overweight i don't think right i think
he's uh
physically more frail yeah so that that
puts some weight so probably
it's it's similar um
and so anyway the uh the possibility
exists but now that trump has
i think been forced to admit covet
because it would have been
difficult you know i i i've heard people
say that maybe this is
phony i think it can't be i don't think
it plays positively for trump so i think
that something that had to be
acknowledged
but i mean it's a it's a hypothesis of
course that's a hypothesis on the table
and you know it occurred i think it
occurred to everyone right like it
has i think most of us who are paying
attention don't trust either of these
parties to be honest with us about this
especially
okay who's how how is which party going
to play this to a win
right right but the question is let's
suppose
biden came down with kobet we now know
he's been in the room in the last week
with a bunch of people who've had it
within you know just a little more than
48 hours of someone
who you know 48 plus hours later
uh tested positive right so
there is a question about him coming
down with it if
trump is sidelined from public
appearances i.e debates
would the biden camp acknowledge it
if it happened i don't think we know but
i must tell you
i don't trust either of these camps to
be straight with us
and the question is you know let's be
adults about this
the amount that is at stake in an
american presidential election
is trillions of dollars right that means
that that's the game being played people
who are
jockeying for position relative to that
massive value that gets
uh controlled in in these
uh contests have a huge incentive
to do whatever makes it most likely that
they will have the influence to pedal
and the other side won't
yeah so in any case the
i don't know what would happen uh
we're biden to get covey but more
importantly the thing i really want to
get to
is in light of the symptoms
that show up with many cases of covid
and in particular these long-haul cases
of covid
right people have brain fog that
goes on for months some people have
things that recur
on them monthly that has implications
for the commander-in-chief
in other words i think we have to be
talking about the question
about whether or not a is he 74
the president yeah sounds about right 74
year old
man who has coveted in october
right is in a position going forward
will we even know if he is in a position
right will his doctors know i don't
think they will know but even if they
knew
would we know what the implication was
of this diagnosis going forward this
disease is so
eclectic with respect to the tissues
that it affects
it is so clearly having cognitive
implications
for people and we don't know what the
long-term prospects are for these long
haulers of which there are many
and the fact is even in our circle i
know people who have long haul problems
with covid so and you know young people
yeah so anyway we have a predicament
where we are now
and you know americans have this bad
tendency to see
everything as the sort of internal to
america discussion
and to forget the international context
where we have
um antagonists around the globe
who you know look at the question of how
fit our commander-in-chief is likely to
be at any given moment
and presumably make strategic decisions
based on that right
so anyway i i don't know how to have
this conversation well but i do have the
feeling that we are not having the
proper conversation which is
a [ __ ] the goddamn duopoly for giving us
two fragile candidates at an
era where you have covid circulating
and you've got uh you know
peril that demands a commander-in-chief
who can
fire it up at a moment's notice and make
good decisions where we cannot have
you know people randomly sidelined and
you know some sort of theater going on
where we don't know how sick they are
and what condition they're in today and
you know the garbage today with the
doctors
playing games around well he's not on
oxygen
now right not on oxygen now
right was he ever on it well he's not on
it now um
that's not like an answer to the
question yeah but i mean i'm sure the
doctors have been told what they are and
aren't allowed to say
so yeah it's we can't we shouldn't blame
them i expect um
you know at some level i'm i'm uh
lowering my threshold of tolerance
because the fact is
yes um this isn't this is bigger than
any individual
right this is bigger than the election
this is about the republic and it is
these processes in which everybody is
policing
you know their own well-being and
adhering to rules that
you know keep them in positions of power
that has put the republic in such a
dangerous
position and so my sense is actually um
you have an obligation to tell us the
truth because this isn't
you know this isn't about president
trump this is about the republic and
whether or not it has a
commander-in-chief who's in a position
to do his job
yep um
can i pivot to just one other little
thing about kovid sure
zack would you show my screen this is uh
september 30th 2020
daily newsletter from the oregon health
authority with the coronavirus update i
get these i think they sent him out five
days a week
um and the september 30th one
was making the headline is making sense
of truth versus rumor
and they talk about how it can be hard
to make sense of what's accurate and
what's not
and they you know suggest various places
where you can go to make sense of
what's accurate what's not and just five
days earlier
in their september 25th uh newsletter
which i also received
they uh quote let's see here at the
bottom here state health officer dean
seidlinger in a media briefing today
advising us that what we all need to do
is stay at least six feet apart from
people outside your household
check restrict your gatherings check
we're
face covering when you're outside the
house or indoors where distancing can't
be achieved
what what that's not just for
superheroes
so i like both parts of that third
bullet point are wrong
wear face covering when you're outside
no you don't need to unless you're in
close quarters in which case you should
or indoors where distancing can't be
achieved
actually indoors unless you're with the
people you're podding with
you're probably a pretty high risk and
you should probably consider wearing a
mask
always now that doesn't fly with people
who have to be sharing buildings with
other people
and it feels like quite a burden but
this is backwards
and this is exactly this is the oregon
health authority
who not five you know five days later
said
don't you know don't be misled by rumors
and innuendo and bad science have we got
some sources for you and yet they're
exactly the ones who are propagating
bad science and and and rumors so you
know no wonder people are confused
fed up feel like the whole thing has
been politicized because it has
and that was that you know trump trump
came out of the gates with us
politicizing
uh kova 19 but everyone seems to be in
on the game at this point yes and the
problem is it has actual material costs
people are
dying because i mean look if you've been
following
the dark horse podcast since we began
our live streams which centered
at in the early phase around covid quite
heavily
you know that we've been building a
model you know
our scientific expertise is not
epidemiological
uh you know in particular but that
we were able to track a bunch of things
that were
coming into uh our comprehension
about what does and does not work you
know how people do and do not contract
it initially we were much more concerned
about fomites that is to say viruses
you pick up from touching things now we
know it's mostly
airborne and aerosolized right and that
these two things are factors
you need to update your model for that
we know
that you know opening windows
has an effect that effectively the
volume of the room you're in
matters a lot and therefore opening
windows effectively increases the volume
of the room that the older you are
the you know lower the threshold at
which you'll be infected
so the point is there's like a dozen
pieces of useful information that
upgrade your model of how not to get
sick and how not to get others sick
and we are still playing with this
garbagey
political description of the virus
that's really more about scolding people
you're not wearing a mask you're one of
them no i'm outside
it's yeah it's scolding people and
except it's it's making people more
tribal
as they walk around and look at each
other on the streets then the number of
times
that i have gotten side eye from people
walking around
outside from a distance you know 20 30
feet away
when i'm not wearing a mask and they are
and you know it could be anything but
that doesn't usually happen to me
right like it's i don't i don't get a
lot of nasty looks normally
and in the last two weeks four weeks six
weeks as
increasingly the messaging around
wear masks outside uh if you care about
yourself and others
and oh oh by the way only wear masks
inside if you really can't keep yourself
safe
well that's [ __ ] and it's confusing
people and it's making people
less kind and less generous and less
sane right
and you know at the beginning of this
there was a proper epidemiological
conversation happening in public which
we described as a relief because we've
never heard it before even with respect
to
serious stuff like the flu so you're
talking about like the pre-print servers
and such or no i'm talking about
actually in public people talking about
how to wash your hands
mask wearing you know doing videos in
which you could
see particles being breathed out by
somebody in different circumstances
all of that was incredibly healthy from
the point of view of oh how do these
terms actually get in you and why do you
get sick right we should have had that
conversation
long before there was covet but
that conversation that healthy
description of what actually gets you
sick and what behaviors actually
reduce the chances that it will happen
has broken down into this political
nonsense of like rules that you can spot
whether somebody's following them
and you know i mean it's life and death
it just simply is and
um the
the trump phenomenon the fact that their
culture of bravado
resulted likely resulted
in the president himself contracting
kovid and people around him having
contracted covid when he has access to
the best
tools and information he's got the best
testing that means people coming through
the door can be tested with the highest
probability
of knowing whether they're actually sick
they could have done anything and what
they did is they believed their own
press and people got sick
and that ought to be scaring the rest of
us into
building a model rather than following
politicized
guidelines that are obviously nonsense
yes
absolutely all right where are we time
why
and 13 zach an hour and 13 minutes well
there were a couple other things we
wanted to cover
shall we leave them for next time
probably so
all right well we will leave them for
next time
if there is a next time oh my god um
yeah so but we will we will be back
in 15 minutes we will be back to answer
your super chat questions that you asked
this hour and that you will be asking
next hour
and um you can also
if you are interested access a private
monthly private two-hour q a
uh that we do um by joining me at my
patreon
you can access um some monthly
conversations that brett has the hundred
dollar one was this morning before our
live stream and the 250 will be tomorrow
and uh you can access the discord at
either of them
and what else yeah the one this morning
was great um
as has happened the last few times
people didn't want the conversation to
end i had to go to get ready for dark
horse but people stayed on and
we're talking with each other because
frankly in a sea of craziness finding a
group of people that's committed to
having a high quality conversation about
where we are and what might happen and
what to think about it um
i think people just find it very very
comforting and people are curious
this is this is a group of what 10 15
people oh it's much bigger than that now
must have been
must have been 20 this morning well yeah
yeah but still still small enough to
feel intimate for everyone to have a
voice if they want it and such
yep and if it grows above a certain
number i will divide it into two
conversations yeah i think we had talked
about sort of over 20
maybe over 25 it's two conversations yep
yeah
anyway it's great and the other one is
great too the other one is more
evolutionarily focused
um there's some overlap between them but
uh anyway they're quite good all right
so find access to those at your patreon
indeed and um ask us questions if you
like
through super chat uh now or at the
beginning of the next hour
as i'll just lay out the the rules that
we
use to decide on questions again we
never get to all of them for which we
apologize we're grateful to your
questions and
for your support uh we go through
and uh pick up the highest dollar value
questions from this first hour
and uh and then read from the next hour
them in order they come in and then we
always start with a few
from the previous episode that we missed
regardless of how much they were at or
when they came in
uh and also often we'll read one that
emerges from the discord server
so a whole whole lot of ways to maybe
get your question answered although
like i said um we don't uh
we don't get to all of them all right we
will see you
in 15 minutes uh don't forget to like
subscribe
notify and uh also
fairfax no okay i know that cat a little
well
i don't think that would be good for the
republic yes you're right all right
be well everyone